<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Magneticall animadversions made by Marke Ridley ... vpon certaine Magneticall advertisements, lately published, from Maister William Barlouu.</title>
            <author>Ridley, Mark, 1560-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15544</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21402616</idno>
  <idno type="VID">178503</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248564335</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 21044</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S1115</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15544)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178503)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1735:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Magneticall animadversions made by Marke Ridley ... vpon certaine Magneticall advertisements, lately published, from Maister William Barlouu.</title>
                  <author>Ridley, Mark, 1560-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 43.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Barlow, William, d. 1625. --  Magneticall advertisements.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Gilbert, William, 1540-1603.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Magnetism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178503:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178503:1"/>
            <p>Magneticall Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made by</hi> Marke Ridley, <hi>Doctor</hi> in Physicke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋpon certaine</hi> Magneticall Advertisements, lately published, <hi>From</hi> Maister WILLIAM BARLOVV.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes.</hi> 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:178503:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178503:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO the Courteous and Iudicious <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an olde prouerbe, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can bee perfect at the first inuention of it; and in an Arte that is new, the more that write of it, the better it is for the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; for from euery man hee may gleane somewhat: and the more any matter is argued, the more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge there will be had of the truth of the matter propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and the falshoodes will so much the sooner be espied. Therefore in reading the Booke of <hi>Magneticall Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisements,</hi> I obserued that the Author had beene indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious in some things; in other things somewhat for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull, deuising some things not so pertinent as hee esteemed they would bee: but no new thing was added, some old things mistaken, some things censured imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly:
<pb facs="tcp:178503:3"/>wherevpon I haue taken alittle paines to make a suruey of this Booke; no way going about to examine all, lest I should seeme either too diligent or too curious; but clearing as well as I could, that which I tooke to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, opening that which I thought to bee obscure, and where any thing was vnprofitably deuised, I made what vse I could of it, or else reiected it; and looke what I thought was mistaken, I haue answered, and made it manifest for all men easilie to vnderstand; wherein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing desirous to satisfie all, I hope that I haue set a way open for euery man to enter in, and tread in the pathes of Truth. The particulars will be better vnderstood in the reading of both Bookes together, then can bee if some of them were here inserted, and therefore wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the courteous and iudicious Reader health and benefit here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I cease,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all affection, <hi>M. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:178503:3"/>
            <head>MAGNETICALL <hi>Animaduersions.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Author of the Treatise of</hi> Magneticall Animaduersions <hi>deliuereth in his Epistle before his Booke to Sir</hi> Dudley Digges, <hi>that he had somewhat entred into the admirable and secret virtues of the Load-stone by the space of these forty yeares, by reading other mens Writings, by his owne industrie and practise: and what he hath collected and found, this little treatise will shew. Which, whether it bee any thing or nothing, hee referreth to the Iudicious Readers consideration; but in speciall, to Sir</hi> Dudley Digges <hi>his fauourable constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and good acceptance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This great allegation of his long and continuall paines for these fortie yeares, in searching out the properties of the Magnet, would draw any man into a wonderfull expectation of very rare, obstruse, labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inuētions, such as the learned wits of the world neuer imagined or suspected would euer haue come to light: but now that they are set abroad in print, all may see what strange inuentions they are, most of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:178503:4"/>them being before set out by doctor <hi>Gilbert,</hi> and there is almost no proposition or portrature in this Booke, which most Mariners Instrument-makers, Compasse-makers, Clocke-makers, Smiths, and Cutlers of the better and more vnderstanding sort about <hi>London</hi> and the Suburbs haue not knowne, practized, and made, long before the Coppy of this Treatise was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to sir <hi>Thomas Challenor</hi> seauen yeares since, who by reason of their daily vse of Load-stones, may likewise prescribe in the virtues of them. For when the Smiths and Cutlers that cut and formed that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Load-stone in the time of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> before Doctour <hi>Gilberts</hi> death, which tooke vp an Anchore weighing about twenty foure pounds in weight, which my Lord <hi>Arundell</hi> then bought of them, with all their implements, and now possesseth: with what practises and experiments did these men driue the people into an admiration of the properties of the Load-stone? and also with what great varietie of trickes and deuices did they wonderfully content the common people, being very subtill and obseruant to learne and increase their skill, not sparing their pains to visit all whom they thought knew any thing in that kinde of practise.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Many yeares since, his friends, some honourable personages before and since Doctor</hi> Gilbers <hi>Booke was printed, and the Doctor himselfe, vnto whom hee had shewed his obseruations, were desirous to haue him publish them, but aboue all, Sir</hi> Thomas Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenor <hi>preuailed most, and hee deliuered him this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise finished as now it is, sauing some new Additions to print, seauen yeares since which was lost, so that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:178503:4"/>three yeares after hee had another sent, and knoweth not what is become of that also: but it is said that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie portratures of his, and propositions, are in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans Booke, who vsurpeth that hee vnderstandeth not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Treatise of his there be not many, or scarse anie propositions or formes, which Doctor <hi>Gilbert</hi> hath not, and I finde by now borrowing your written Coppie, which I neuer sawe but one night before, that this Booke hath not halfe so many formes or tipes as your Booke hath, which are but very few, and very easie to be inuented; so that if you had named, and noted the portratures and propositions you do claime as your owne, then the matter had sooner beene answered, then now it can be roued at. And I know verie well, that some noble personages, and others haue had some few formes, now by you set downe, made them by Smiths, and Instrument-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and many other fine formes and implements Magneticall: I gesse some long time before your late Coppies came forth, and such as none hath as yet set forth, being oppropriate vnto their owne cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banet; so that a man may wonder at this mans ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weening of his owne Inuentions and witte, that hee would tie all vnder his conceit, not to deuise or know any thing that he thinketh that hee knoweth, where most of those propositions and deuices, that he vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in this booke, are most of thē in Doctor <hi>Gilberts</hi> Booke, as I said before, or else such ordinarie things that any ingenious workeman hath or may easily in uent and make; vnlesse you hold al men <hi>Dulberts</hi> like your rare workmā of <hi>Winchester,</hi> whō our master work
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178503:5"/>men of <hi>London</hi> account a very bungler; neither boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it much who doth owne them, whereas in trueth, learning and ingenious deuices are subiect to al men, that shall study and labour curiously in the same: and what reason is there that you should take what you list out of Doctor <hi>Gilberts</hi> Booke, as you say in the Preface, and somwhat out of mine, and yet go about in bad terms to deny that libertie vnto others. If you had printed your deuices first, before Doctor <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> set forth his Booke, or presently vpon it: then had you beene Authour of these matters, but now you make claime too late, when all men possesse them, before you Printed this Treatise or gaue out your written Coppies; and such as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired the same of you, peraduenture expected from fortie yeares practise, greater matters then these, which, no doubt, they knew for the most part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreouer, you say in the Preface, that you may truely affirme, that searching with diligence Doctor</hi> Gilberts <hi>first fiue Bookes, you found all things agreeable to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent obseruations of diuers men of experience, although in some matters of the Load-stone his experiments and yours did disagree, for which you haue his letters to shew: and concerning the sixt Booke entreating of the Motion of the Earth, you doe no whit beleeue it, by any perswasions out of the reasons he produceth out of other men, or by his owne inuentions from Magneticall force, to proue the Earths motion, which you thinke to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you seeme to taxe Doctor <hi>Gilbert</hi> for hauing magneticall Experiments disagreeing from yours,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:178503:5"/>whereof you admonished him in his life time, and he tooke it in good part, his bookes are in print for all men to read, your exceptions you doe not make knowen either in this Preface; or in your booke fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, therefore I hold this a needlesse imputation, making your selfe both a secret accuser and Iudge, <hi>But his sixt booke can no waies bee acceptable vnto you, being for fortie yeares a Student in Magniticall Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophie, and daily conuersant in his Bookes,</hi> I wish you had set downe your reasons, why you persist in a contrary opinion vnto him. If I might bee so bold I desire to aske you this question; it is written in the first Chapter of <hi>Genises</hi> the sixth verse, that God made the Firmament before hee cleered and made the earth, in the 10. verse; I would demaund what this Firmament was? is it not <hi>expausuum tennissimam vniuersi, in quo omnia ponuntur &amp; mouentur.</hi> For wheresoeuer wee trauell, wee see the brightnesse and thinnesse of it, and most of the Globes and Starres placed and moouing in it: Then the next thing I would learne is, whether when God created the Earth, hee did not lay the foundation thereof in this Firmament as wee see other Globes to be, as the Psamist King <hi>Dauid</hi> recordeth, that God hath laied the foundation of the world, and all that therein is. <hi>Psalme</hi> 89 <hi>verse</hi> 11. where in the 12 <hi>verse</hi> hee saith that God created the North and the South, which in my opinion is as much as if hee should say that God created the <hi>Magneticall</hi> vertues, as we terme it of North and South in the earth, to hold him sure as vpon a foundation from altering his position, and placing North and South, in his iust eleuation,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178503:6"/>and therefore it is true that the earth is thus firmely seated by virtue tending from the whole body to the two Poles, as I haue demonstrated in my Booke of <hi>Magneticall bodies and Motions;</hi> likewise in the 48 <hi>Chapter</hi> of <hi>Ieb</hi> the 4 and 5 <hi>verses,</hi> God telleth <hi>Iob,</hi> that he laied the foundation of the earth, with all the measures thereof, and the line ouer it. VVhereby I conceiue, that God founded and seated the earth by Magneticall vertue in the North and South, and the measures thereof and lines be <hi>Meridians, Parra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lels,</hi> and <hi>aequinoctiall</hi> line, whereby Trauellers and Marriners measure the earth about, both by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Longitude, and also by the Degrees of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, so that this is a true Maxime and Axiome that <hi>Deus &amp; natura nihil fecerunt frustra.</hi> That wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is an aequator on the body of the earth and parralells thereunto, which haue no power Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall to retaine themselues in any place, but all such abilities of retention passe with the Meridians, to fortifie and make a sure stay at the Poles in the North &amp; South, what natural thing can there be that should hinder the Globe of the earth thus firmly fixed on his Poles to keepe his seat in the North and South from mouing other parts, which can resist no vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous power that is able to turne his whole body round about, as it were vpon an Axoltree from the West towards the East, and if the earthes weight and grauitie might peraduenture be an hinderance hereunto, then thereis an other Axiome that <hi>nihil in proprio loco graue,</hi> or rather that <hi>nil mobile insuoper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto vigore graue,</hi> for let a man be in youth, health, and perfect strength, it is not a wearinesse but a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:178503:6"/>pleasure to walke and mooue; but in these great Globes and Starres, whose vigour and power is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eternall with the world, God hath set an ordinance that shall not passe, and as it is in the meeter; <hi>To them he made, a Law and trade for aye to last,</hi> Psal. 148.6. Now I would learne what Ordinance, Law and Trade these Globes and Starres haue, which are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in this thin Firmanent, which are coaeternall with the world; and which shall continue as long as the world shall last, if it be not there indefatigable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to moue naturally, or erraticably like baly er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants to turne about, to giue and receiue thee light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somes beames and influences benefitiall one to an other, and to make other motions about their Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, according vnto the faculties giuen them at their creation. And who is there that can imagine that the Earth being mother of so many Infants, as shee is enioyned presently vpon the Creation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>vers.</hi> 11.12. to bring forth should be such a lasie and vnkinde nourse, that shee should onely foster them with the naturall heat of her bosome, and to take no paines to moue and turne her selfe about, and carrie them all to receiue indifferently the liuely and warme beames and lights of the Sunne and Starres, which were created the day after, verses 16, 17, 18, 19. These things I haue set downe, not hoping to perswade you any whit, or others who are to much adicted to that they sucked from their youth out of Philosophers, which all Schollers read after they haue beene two yeares in the Vniuersities, especially from their old friend <hi>Aristotle, whom you say you would forsake to embrace the truth,</hi> and though many
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178503:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:178503:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:178503:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:178503:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:178503:9"/>things of great moment in him of Philosophie and Anotomy were confuted demonstratiuely by <hi>Galen</hi> long since, yet because all read the first, and very few the latter, but onely professors in Physicke, so that his opinions are almost imbraced by all, yet now in these daies, where <hi>dies Diemdocet,</hi> by the multitude of the writings and labours of late most learned Writers, it is come to bee an vsuall assertion in the Schooles that, <hi>in Anatomicis &amp; Astronomies errauit Aristoteles;</hi> and certainely if wee shall obserue and ponder what a thing the wonderfull vastnesse of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pansion, the fine and thin Firmament hath, and what a great distance there is betweene the earth and the farthest limits (for Spheres are but fained) of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of <hi>Saturne</hi> from the earth, but especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the fixed Starres, which are held to be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as farre againe and much mooue from <hi>Saturne,</hi> it might be said, that the earth firmed in her positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might mooue her whole bodie many thousand miles from place to place, and yet there would bee found no excentritie of the fixed starres by the earth, and all those arguments which are vsed by <hi>Aristotle, Ptolomie, Regiomontamis, Iohannes de Sacrobosco</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to proue, that the earth is <hi>centrum vniuersi</hi> would bee no otherwise, then now they are, for the earth is not <hi>centrum vniuersi,</hi> but is as it were <hi>pūctum insensibile respectu vniuersi &amp; stellarum fixarum,</hi> and no doubt but that <hi>Copernicus</hi> and <hi>Tichobrahe</hi> most perfect and exact Astronomers, who make the Sunne to be <hi>centrum vniuersi &amp; planetarum</hi> accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the said arguments and proofes to be of force, and as truely verified of the Sunne, as of the earth if
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:178503:9"/>a man might passe thether to trie the same, and whereas you professe your selfe to be so diligent a reader of Doctor <hi>Gilberts</hi> bookes, most worthie of great commendations for his first inuentions, and great paines in the Magneticalls, that you would a little peruse Master <hi>Wrights</hi> Epistle vnto him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed before his booke; hee was a verie skilfull and painefull man in the Mathematickes, a worthy rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of that lecture of Nauigation for the East-Indian Company, and it is a great defect to that art, that that Lecture should not bee continued and more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally maintained, their gaines being so great, this man tooke great paines in correcting the printing of Doctor <hi>Gilberts</hi> booke, and was very conuersant with him; I hauing often conferred with him, and considering of the sixt booke which you no way beleeue, I asked whether it was any way of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king or assistance, for that I knew him most perfect in <hi>Copernicus</hi> from his youth, and he denied that hee gaue any aide thereunto, I replied that the 12 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the 4 Booke must needs be his, because of the table of the fixed Starres, so he confessed that hee was the Author of that Chapter, and inquiring fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whether he obserued the Author skilfull in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernicus, he answered that hee did not, then it was found that one Doctor <hi>Gissope</hi> was much esteemed by him, and lodged in his house whom we knew al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to be a great Scholler in the Mathematick, who was a long time entertained by Sir <hi>Charles Chandish,</hi> hee was a great assistance in that matter as we iudged, and I haue seene whole sheetes of this mans owne hand writing of Demonstrations to this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:178503:10"/>purpose out of Copernicus, in a booke of Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie copied out in an other hand, this man should haue succeeded me in Russia, had not God called him by death to a better place.</p>
            <p>Now at length wee come to your booke, where your needles discourse of electricall attraction inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptteth your Doctrin of your <hi>long piece of clay, burnt in the fire, and laied to coole, with his ends North and South.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You say in the fourth page that that end which cooled towards the South, will draw the true North end of the needle, and that end which cooled towards the North, wil draw the true South end of the needle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This assertion might very well haue beene one of those differences you say, was betweene you and Doctor <hi>Gilbert,</hi> if you had printed it as it was in your written coppie without that word True, which I haue borrowed to read with your printed booke, and so it had beene contrary to all experience, but by inser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that word of equiuocation, you may make any thing of it either way, for you tell vs that the <hi>true North end, will draw the true South end of the directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie needle,</hi> as though there were a true and a false South-end, and a true and a false North-end; why doe you not set downe that you teach certainely, for thus you may make chalke cheese, and cheese chalke; either call that North, that keepeth the North; and that South that aspecteth the South, or else you had better say nothing, and so you should not distract the Reader, for we call all that dwell on this side the riuer of Trent, Southeren men though some were borne in Yorkeshire, and all Northren
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:178503:10"/>men that dwell on the North-side of the riuer Trent. For these be two things to animate and to aspect; needles are animated from the North-pole of the Load-stone, but aspecteth the South Prouince of the Earth, and is to be called a South-end, and so it is a rule in all Magneticall endowments at the first, that if you hang this burnt clay by a thread or rush fastened about the middest of it, then that end that cooled North, and was excited from the North Prouince of the Magneticall Globe of the Earth, will turne it selfe South, and so alwaies rest it selfe, and neuer will serue on the North-side, and if you had set downe this deuise for Marriners and others to practise it, that at such times as it shall please God that they should suffer ship-wracke, and escape by pieces of the shippe, or other happy meanes to any vnknowne or vnhabited land; yet they might, hauing lost all but their liues, by this deuise haue vsed it as a Marriners compasse to direct them to the place where they first arriued, or some other neere conuenient shore to watch whether any shippes passed that way to carrie home vnto their natiue countrie againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreouer wheras you haue added in the</hi> 10 <hi>page, which is not in your written Copie, that if a weake Load-stone be excited from a strong Magnet at both the ends with one Pole, that the violence of it driueth the contrary vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue into the middest of it, where being deuided will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently shew the contrarie propertie vnto the other two ends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching the trench hereof in weake Magnets I will stay a while to make experience of it, because
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:178503:11"/>it is not so easie a thing for to deuide and saw a sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Magnets presently, but this I dare assure you that in a wyer excited at both ends frō one pole, this assertion is not true, for deuide this wyer in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest and the parts cut a sunder, wilbe of a countrary nature on to the other, and but one of the other two ends will hold his first endowment.</p>
            <p>As concerning your second Chapter, where you <hi>insert a matter of ambiguitie,</hi> whether to iustifie that you set downe in the fourth page or no, wee may doubt, <hi>and that which you affirme out of Doctor</hi> Gilbert, <hi>to call that ende North which aspecteth the North, would ouerthrow the frame and foundation of Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Philosophie, if it bee seriously defended,</hi> there can be no such cause of feare as you answere your selfe <hi>Loquendum vt vulgus,</hi> for <hi>as you say in the</hi> 12 <hi>page</hi> in my words <hi>ends of like denomination will flie the one the other,</hi> also you say in the 13 page, <hi>That it is the true South-end that pointeth to the North, and the true North end that looketh towards the South,</hi> you should rather and more truely haue said, that that end that pointeth towards the North was a part animated from the South Prouince of the Load-stone, so cut out of his mine, or from a great stone, and thus shall you leaue all equiuocating ambiguities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the latter end of the</hi> 14 <hi>page you vtter a contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to that you taught in the</hi> 13 <hi>page, that parts cut off Meridionally will point as the entire did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being false and contrarie to that you set down <hi>in the</hi> 13 <hi>page</hi> before, and contrary also to Doctor <hi>Gilbert, fol.</hi> 100. deserueth no other confutation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the</hi> 15 <hi>page you teach this doctrine that dissagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:178503:11"/>of the ends is onely within the Orbe of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but not in their generall disposition to the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It seemeth, that that your iudgement is very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine; <hi>for in the</hi> 12. <hi>and</hi> 13 <hi>page you taught the cleane contrarie to this, and to your opinion afterwards in the</hi> 43 <hi>page at large deliuered, because a part cut off is</hi> totum integrale, <hi>and seuered, will disagree from the entire or great one,</hi> in the latter end of this page you make a needlesse repetition of that you spoake of in the 12 page afore.</p>
            <p>In the 26. and 27 pages, you haue inserted, that which is not in the written coppie, but it is more new then true, whose tipe you haue set downe in the 22 page, the matter is thus, <hi>If that the Poles bee not in the ends of the long Oual Magnet, then this long stone will not point vnto the Magneticall North and South, but falsly, and by this experiment you may so order the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, that you may make him stand to any point of the Compasse whatsoeuer. Also you may so touch the wiers of the Compasse, that the Flower-de-lice shall stand to any point, although the wyers bee iustly fastened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is somewhat a deformed proposition you adde here, but it is altogether vntrue if the Magnet be vigorous, for shift the threed so that the Poles may be set leuell with the Horizon, and the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone hanging thus, will point out the Magneticall Meridian, or else place him in his boate on the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and hee will seat himselfe North and South, for all round Magnets, formes of many corners, all rude formes though as rough and deformed as they were broken frō the Rock, hauing their Poles placed leuell
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:178503:12"/>with the Horizon, being put into a boate loaden with sand for that purpose, all these will rest their Poles North and South, and not to euery point of the Compasse as you write, <hi>Also you tell vs of a new deuise to touch the wiers of Compasses to turne to any point,</hi> but I gesse your wiers must be of or nere a roūd forme, not straight, <hi>which forme you commend though vntruely in the</hi> 68 <hi>page, to bee the best forme for wiers, or of a steele plated ring for Compasses,</hi> which I hope you will not maintaine, because you teach more truely in the 60 page, <hi>that the Magneticall force must passe along in the true axis,</hi> and these round wiers or plates haue no axis, or a very short on, if not two, but if I would goe about to tell falshoods, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the reader therewith, I can say, that if you touch a ring of steele or iron in twenty places with one pole, and after touch as many opposite places with the other pole, then bring the needle of your diall to the ring, and it will point and turne to all these contrarie touches you made, first by one point, and then by the other point, as the nature of the touches were, and therefore I may conclude that this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position is vnperfect, vnprofitable and very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be followed, for my part I thinke you had done more aduisedly to haue left it out of your booke, being a new toy to lately hatched.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You propound in the</hi> 32 <hi>page, this conceit of your long Ouall Load-stone with two teeth, taking vp more with them, or rather twise as much, as either end taketh vp seuerally; because the virtue of both ends of the stone is infused into both the ends of the capitell of iron, and the violence of both these virtues in the ends doe striue
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:178503:12"/>to repell his contrarie vnto his proper end, hereby either end becommeth the stronger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This conceit is your owne, but it is contrary to other your propositions in this booke, but how doe the ends of a wier or a capitell receiue their virtue? but by touching and exciting from the Load-stone; for if you touch any wier at one end, the virtue of that Pole goeth but to the middest of it, and the contrary virtue vnto the other end, <hi>and all Magneticall force is strongest in the ends as you set downe in the</hi> 63 <hi>page,</hi> and the middest is weakest; therefore the force of touching is not repelled into the ends, by the North or South propertie but is there naturally, as in his poles, and this square piece of iron, is as it were a thicke wyer excited at once at both ends from the two teeth of the Load-stone; so that this thing is no <hi>violent driuing to be stronger then otherwise it would bee</hi> 31 <hi>page</hi> but naturall as being vnited vnto the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, I pray you to <hi>obserue your proofe and demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, how all the virtue is in the ends of the long piece of iron:</hi> A. and this you endeauor to prooue by <hi>three other square Capitells that haue brasse in the middest, as</hi> B. <hi>more.</hi> C. <hi>lesse and</hi> D. <hi>least brasse of them all.</hi> A. <hi>being all of iron is held fast,</hi> B. <hi>hauing most brasse and least iron applied to the two teeth of the Magnet is held weakely,</hi> C. <hi>hauing more iron then</hi> B. <hi>being applied is held more strongly,</hi> D. <hi>with least brasse and most iron is retained most strongly in comparison of the other two</hi> B. <hi>and</hi> C. if the virtue were most in the ends and teeth, why should not B. bee strongly held by his short pieces of iron in the ends of the Capitell, that fitteth the ends rather then the midst space, C. <hi>is held
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:178503:13"/>better; and</hi> D. <hi>better then both the other</hi> B. <hi>and</hi> C. <hi>but clappe</hi> B.C.D. <hi>and</hi> A. <hi>altogether one aboue the other, but</hi> A. <hi>must bee lowest, as it is in the</hi> 32 <hi>page, then the two teeth of the Load-stone will lift them all vp together ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie easily,</hi> the iron parts being like an halfe-moone: he had need haue his wits together to obserue what this demonstration and businesse proueth, in my conceit it proueth not <hi>that the virtue is most in the ends of</hi> A. but that the teeth will rather take vp a great whole piece of iron, then two little pieces, or that that pieces with most iron is held alongest the middest better then at both ends, or that wee may make a Capitell of iron like an halfe-moone as well as a straight one, therefore all this is vnprofitable to proue this position that the strength is violently driuen into the ends of A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Also in the</hi> 33 <hi>page you haue another conceit, that the Capitell being ioyned to both the teeth will extend his virtue downeward scarse halfe an inch at his ends, by reason of the striuing of the virtue to make the Capitell strong at both the ends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this I gather that the ends are strong to hold, but vnfit to send virtue downeward, but I hold them no way fortified by any striffe of virtue, as you haue imagined which no way by these deuises is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated, <hi>But contrary hereunto in the</hi> 34 <hi>page, you proue rather that the force of taking vp is in the middle of the Capitell, rather then in the ends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the</hi> 36 <hi>page you would haue two prominent pieces of iron fitted for, and to the image of</hi> Arsinoe <hi>or such like made of anie light stuffe for to take hold of the two teeth of a long Ouall Load-stone, placed in the roofe of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:178503:13"/>some building,</hi> and no doubt but this deuise of yours would proue as conuenient, as your <hi>Capitell of</hi> B. <hi>with much intermediat brasse, which is the worst Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitell for retention, that you propounded page</hi> 31.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the</hi> 40 <hi>page in conioyning and piecing Load-stones together, you ioyne North to North, and South to South, but in the</hi> 42 <hi>page, if your egge forme bee sawen a sunder in the middest, then if you attempt to ioyne the two halfes together, againe in length you doe ioyne them at like ends, a thing directly repugnant to the principles of Magneticall Philosophie, yet in the</hi> 43 <hi>page if you place these precisely as they were at first, they will agree toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as one and the same Magnet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a mingle mangle of contrarieties, <hi>they will conioyne being of like name, if you doe conioyne the like ends together, it is directly repugnant to this arte,</hi> and yet they will <hi>agree as one Magnet,</hi> so that heere you say and vnsay, and yet say and affirme againe the same thing, so that here you play fast and loose with Magneticall principles at your pleasure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In teaching to finde the variation of the Magneticall Meridian, from the true Meridian in the</hi> 46 <hi>page, you doe define it rightly, to the sweruing of the Magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call needle in the Horizon from the true Meridian;</hi> but in the latter end of this same page, <hi>you vse the helpe of an other Circle called an Almicanther,</hi> which is a circle of Allitude, so called of all that wright of the Sphere, first in the definition of the variation you thought the Horizontall circle sufficient to shew it, and to get the quantitie of it which way it lieth Easterly or Westerly, so that for this purpose there is no need of any other as of an Almicanther circle,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:178503:14"/>which is a little circle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Presently after in the</hi> 47 <hi>page, you tell vs of a Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neticall respectiue Pole, which you say is the Pole of the Magneticall Meridian, which is so much distant from the true Pole, as the variation is; and it is as farre off the verticall point, as the true Pole is, &amp; is of the same height aboue the Horizon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is strange to obserue how hee runneth on with this respectiue pole in a Magnetiall Meridian, as thought it were very true, and a thing confessed by all, but indeed it is a new matter neuer heard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or at least neuer allowed by any that was skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Magneticall Philosophie, or by your selfe in an other, as shall appeare presently, I had thought that Doctor <hi>Gilbert</hi> had so refuted these respectiue Poles, fained by diuers, whom hee nameth with the Magneticall Mountaines on the earth, so as the world would neuer haue beene deceiued with them againe, or that any man should imagine that euer there was any such matter in truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And you your selfe in your written copie, whereof you had another copie vnder this mans hand, deliuered you by the partie that lent me now this copie, professe in your Epistle vnto Sir</hi> Thomas Challenor, <hi>that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why you write this Treatise was, because you had seene a discourse called Niecometria Magnetica, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by a French man, that vnderstood not the Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Doctrine, and therefore missed far on the marke he aimed at, which man also calculated laborious tables frō a wrong &amp; erroneus foundation, namely frō his supposed fixednes of the Magneticall Poles of the Earth, in the two polar circles, or neare the same within some few minutes,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:178503:14"/>because you would be loath, that many or any of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion should bee carried away with this or the like vaine position; you haue made somewhat the more hast to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish this booke,</hi> therefore what a great noueltie or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgetfulnesse is it, that you should discourse of Magneticall Poles in the same Almicanter and hight with the Pole, disliking the same matter, but a little different so highly in an other: but it may be that you will answere, that you speake here of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectiue Poles and not of fixed poles as other haue done,</hi> I pray you in examining the variation, doth the Flower-de-lice or the needle respect any poles, I hope you will not affirme it although you talke here of respectiue poles, what way then shall we fish out your meaning? <hi>In the</hi> 21 <hi>page, you bid vs make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectiue or declinatorie needle, and by his axis to put him on a forked sticke,</hi> I iudge that now wee haue catched what you doe meane; belike this respetiue needle, will aspect your respectiue poles, and here I am afraide that by ignorance of the Magneticals and true vse of this needle, you will runne your shippe on ground, where these new Load-starres or poles will no way aduantage you, doe you thinke that this respectiue needle will point at your respectiue poles; it is certaine that it mounteth vp with the one point, being placed in his ring or boxe, and descendeth with the other end vnder the Horizon, but whether in this scituation he respecteth and pointeteth to the true Altitude of the respectiue poles is a matter which hereafter shalbe decided; and first I will proue that by your assertion there is not onely two, but many respectiue poles, and that shalbe thus, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectiue
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:178503:15"/>poles are many almost infinite, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not onely two; moreouer all respectiue poles are in number proportioned to the vanitie of varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but there bee many and almost infinit sorts of variations <hi>as you instruct vs in the</hi> 53 <hi>and</hi> 54 <hi>pages;</hi> therefore therebe many, and almost an infinit num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of respectiue poles, which if you shall grant, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what a multitulde of absudities will you fall? for though that variations should be infinit, yet it is not necessarie that they should haue any poles or whole Meridians at all, being wholy measured and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon the Horizon from the true Meridian to the needles point, which needeth not to be called a Magneticall Meridian, being but a line of position called so for distinction sake, and not in truth, and then if there bee no whole continued Magneticall Meridians, how can there then bee any respectiue poles?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore in the latter end of the</hi> 53 <hi>page, you propound a truth of this matter, from a round vnperfect Load-stone, that hath weake matter of a Load-stone or other corrupt stuffe in it, then take a little needle of a Diall, and set it vpon the sound part of the Load-stone, and it will point on that Meridian towards the true Pole of the Magnet, after set this needle where the part is weake and corrupt, then it will point and respect an other Pole, againe set it to another false part, and the needle will respect neither of these former Poles,</hi> thus in a multiude of impefections you shall finde the needle to point according to euery particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and if you should goe about to ioyne the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of resting the needle, you shall trace out a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:178503:15"/>crooked line or circle, for <hi>rectum est vnicum, obliquum infinitum,</hi> therefore these kinde of circles cannot be called Magneticall Meridinns, but rather falshoods, imperfections and deuiations from the truth, now we shall prooue that your respectiue nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle so tearmed of you, doth not respect the Altitude of the respectiue Pole, for although hee hath an as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cension aboue the Horizon, yet it is alwaies a great deale more then the eleuation of the pole of the world is, and therefore cannot any waies <hi>behold and aspect the respectiue Pole as you write being in the same Almicanter and Altitude with the Pole of the world,</hi> but must needs ouershoot him farre, vnlesse the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation should be made iust vnder the Pole, and the truth is for ought that I can finde in this Booke, you haue vttered almost nothing to informe vs that you doe vnderstand Doctor <hi>Gilberts</hi> fift booke, or the nature of the conuersion of this needle partly set out in other his former bookes; now to tell you the truth; the inclinatory needle maketh alwaies one kinde of angle in one and the same eleuation of the pole, and in one parralell, but the variation in one parralell is diuers and most vncertaine, for it may be 10.20. or 30. degrees and so infinitly, then accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly you must find out such like respectiue poles in your Almicanter remoued accordingly from the true pole, both in the foresaid places and in infinit others, therefore these respectiue poles being vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine infinit and vnprofitable, are therefore to bee reiected as things fained, and in themselues meerely false, so that it is a thing absolutely vnnecessary, that when you teach to finde the variation from the true
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:178503:16"/>Meridian vpon the Horizon, you must needes enter into a discourse of describing the same <hi>Magneticall Meridian, which you would haue passe by the respectiue Pole in that same Almicanter with the Pole of the world,</hi> for if the quantitie of variation be plainely found vpon the Horizon, by sinding out the true Meridian, you hauing but one point of a Magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Meridian, as I may truely affirme, which if you should follow but one mile or lesse, you shall leese your Meridian quite, and enter in an other, for if you could sinde it much further to hold out, yet it will not cause the variations thereof to bee all one and of the same quantitie; and this was the thing that deceiued <hi>Gulielmus Nantonerius,</hi> that he set downe his <hi>Magneticall poles as you say about the polar Circle,</hi> and <hi>Antony Linton</hi> our countriman, whose laborious workes likewise neuer came to the presse, being deciued with the like matter, wherefore I hope that hereafter all fixed and respectiue poles with their Meridians wilbe vtterly exploded from all mens bookes, and vtterly obliterated and blotted out as though they had neuer beene sained.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Further in the</hi> 48 <hi>page, you affirme that an Axis is the line of variation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is taught a Doctrine much differing from the vnderstanding of the Sphere, or of the proiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof in <hi>Plano,</hi> for variation being a declinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the point of the needle or Compasse from the true Meridian, is obserued and found by lines of position or azaemuthes, and need not any axis or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian Diamiter to shew it other, then the said lines from the Center of the Horizon. I am very forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:178503:16"/>if you doe not deliuer vnto vs in some place of this booke it may be about the 74 page, <hi>That a needle well and artificially excited and touched: will keepe the saide touch a mans life time and longer.</hi> Yet I thought good to set downe what I larely herd that Sir <hi>Thomas Rowe,</hi> who was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> from the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Mogoll</hi> in <hi>India,</hi> being verie skilfull in Nauigation, and very painefull in obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the variations of his voyage, found the varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be but one degree about the <hi>Cape of good hope,</hi> and so coasting along the East-side of <hi>Affricke,</hi> euen vnto the Islands without the mouth of the Red-sea to the riuer Indus, found the variation of the needle to increase by degrees till it varied about twenty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, but that which is most memorable, is this, that in comparing his variations with other mens, hee found this difference, that hee touching his owne Compasse, and some others euery ten daies, these variations for the most part, obserued from a quicker and more liuely touch, did alwaies exceed the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations of other Compasses, onely touched at home in <hi>England</hi> about some three degrees, which sheweth that the Magenitall vigour will spend and proue weake and exhausted in these hot voyages in <hi>Torrida Zana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You affirme in the</hi> 50 <hi>page, that a continent in the vast Ocean will not cause a variation of declination, in the Inclinatory instrument, which was Doctor</hi> Gilberts <hi>feare, because his hanging is but in length and breadth, and not in depth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although that the frame of the Inclinatory nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle be such by the crosse-barre in the ring, that it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:178503:17"/>cannot bee much drawne awry side-long to a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Magneticall continent, yet no doubt, the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle being subiect to attraction will be a little drawen aside, so that at least he will play more stifly vpon his Axis, then if hee were free from collaterall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, and by this meanes his libertie is barred from moouing truely to his due angle, and though that this exception hindreth this needle but a little, yet there is a variation of the Inclinatory needle from his due angle, as Magneticall forces shalbe placed either before or behind him, as I haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in my booke of <hi>Magneticall bodies and Motions,</hi> which thing any man may make experience of vpon the round Magnet; but to be informed <hi>what your length, breadth and depth meaneth,</hi> we had need of an Oedipus to open it vnto vs, and though you doe denie a variation of the Inclinatory needle in this place, <hi>Yet in the</hi> 49 <hi>page you affirmed a variation of both the needles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreouer in the</hi> 56 <hi>page, you haue this saying, That that end that pointeth to the North, will hang downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, yea although you touch him with the South-end of the Magnet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue two very good Load stones, the one about seauen pound weight, the other of three pounds weight, if you giue a sleight touch to the Inclinato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry needle from the North-pole of the Load-stone, by the ouer-weight of the touch, as I take it, <hi>It will hang downe-ward on the North-side of the Horizon neare</hi> 20.30. <hi>or more degrees, as the touah is, in heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and your opinion concurreth with</hi> Doctor Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert, fol. 186. <hi>and the other end will ascend aboue the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:178503:17"/>Horizon on the Sought-side of the Instrument,</hi> so that this needle thus scituted will haue an Axis descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by his Centre towards the North; when I be held first of all, this position of this needle it seemeth very strange vnto me, but vnto others very familiar and ordinary, and if there should be any other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, the fault did seeme to men of experience to proceed from some thing amisse in the needle, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in forme or matter, or some other attractiue matter in the instrument about it, or in it, and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which is set downe <hi>by you in the</hi> 47. page where <hi>you would haue this respectiue needle as you call it, to behold the respectiue Pole so termed by you, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quantitie of the variation from the true Meridian, the respectiue pole shall differ so much from the true pole,</hi> comparing this scituation of this Axis, which the other supposed Axis aspecting the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectiue pole, and obseruing that it was verie oblique thereunto, and did crosse the former Axis from the respectiue pole, and did so differ in such an vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected manner, that that pole which you termed to bee a respectiue pole, aspected by that needle with vs: On the Noth side of the Zenith about an eleuen Degrees towards the East from the true pole, is now by this new position of this respectiue needle noted to bee on the South side of the Zenith so many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to the West, as it was afore towards the East, so that now by this new doctrine some respectiue Magneticall poles are on our South Meridian side, a matter neuer so much as dreamed of by any, that I could euer heare of, therefore I hope that this asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will not bee approued of by any, no not by your
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:178503:18"/>selfe after that you shall haue better considered of this matter and consequence, being a practise most manifestly repugnant to Magneticall Philosophie, for that all position of poles and axis is from the Noth in our Hemi-sphere to the South-pole or part vnder our Horizon, and that there bee no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectiue poles in the South part aboue our Horizon, either on the North or South-side of the Zenith is a matter that al men will now I think easily assent vnto.</p>
            <p>Therefore this matter and point of touching the Inclinatory needle is to bee melted and coyned a fresh, that the true stampe may appeare, and the old called in againe; and now againe take this Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory needle and excite him perfectly, from the pole or tooth of an excellent and strong Load-stone; that the vigour thereof may infuse a virtue into the needle, able and powerfull to ouer-rule the abstacle and resistance of the heauinesse and weight of the touch; then place this needle in his instrumēt &amp; ring alwaies marking the North-end, which will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend, but ascend aboue our Horizon on the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side of our Hemi-sphere as I haue often tried with diuers needles a foot long, which the smaller and narrower they are the better will the vigour of the Magneticall Globe of the earth, erect them aboue the Horizon, especially if the ends of the needles be not ouer-charged with a crosse or Flower-de-lice or such like, and being artificially animated as I haue said, putting them into their great hanging instrument; as also I put other the like needles into a ring, and frame of sixe inches diamiter, that stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on his foote with a little directory needle
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:178503:18"/>thereon, and then the North-end will ascend, therefore against the former receiued opinion the truth of this businesse shall by this meanes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to all, and I shalbe readie to shew any these needles and instruments, which their true scituation as I haue declared that shall desire it, to see the North end of the needle to ascend, and the South-end to hang downe-ward vnder our Hemi-sphere, and this matter will thus fall out whether you doe excite the needle from the North-end of the Magnet, or from the South, or from both; so that now I hope wel, that hereafter their wilbe no contradiction made herein by any that shalbe indifferent and iudicious, and not to much selfe opinionated in his owne conceit with out better and truer experience hereof; and one thing more is to bee obserued in this inclinatory needle, that that end which is excited and touched from the North-pole of the Magnet, will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert it selfe into the South, but still will keepe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe on the North-side contrary to the course of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectorie needles and compasses, which being exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the North doe presently turne South by the disposition from the earth, yet I haue obserued that the needle being excited from the North, and then if you take of this touch from the South-pole, the North-end will conuert and turne South.</p>
            <p>And I am perswaded that the reason why this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent instrument is not taken into more continuall and frequent vse, is because the true making and touching of the Inclinatory needle hath not beene rightly practised, nor his ascending on the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side any way demonstrated, but that the makers of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:178503:19"/>this instrument haue alwaies made the needle to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend on the North-side, to seuentie two Degrees here with vs, which may bee done by often and easie touching to descend to this Degree or any other, or else by siling the South-end, and so haue deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to bee vsed as truely excited, which thing hath beene a great abuse, and hath shewed a great ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in the makers, and the Marriners haue beene greatly deceiued with this dealing, not able to make any good obseruation by this so profitable an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument, being skilfull and righted mayed and vsed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the end of this Booke you adde a new Chapter, and in the</hi> 81. <hi>page, you begin to finde fault with a picture of the Inclinatory and directorie needles, which I haue des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to bee placed together in one Instrument in the</hi> 143 <hi>page of my booke, which is that these needles there placed bee with in two inches one of the other, and so the Orbes of their vertue bee too neere, and the one of them will hinder the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You should haue considered what was written in the text, and read and weighteth the same; where it is aduised that head be taken that the needles bee not one within an others Orbe, and also you should haue had so much vnderstanding, that in tipes and figures the true distance of the matters specified in the text cannot alwaies bee demonstrated and described in their true proportion, in little plates and pages: and all our great Mathematisians which set downe the Orbes of all the Starres planely, and elements doe set it fourth in a little page, but cannot present to our sight and vew, the true distances and positions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:178503:19"/>but onely a little shew of their scituation, the which if it should be perfectly represented vnto vs would require not onely a sheete of papour, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a large field thereof, and yet the distances would be vnperfect and scanted for roome, so that an offer to wise men in these matters is sufficient.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You allcage in the latter end of the</hi> 81 <hi>page, that the little needle in the bottome of that instrument will giue little direction for that purpose.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainely he that should vse the Inclinatory nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, as you would haue him, had need be a man of great obseruance, that could place this needle North and South perfectly without a directory needle and compasse for that purpose, either within an house, or cabbine, or abroad in cloudy weather, and this thing Doctor <hi>Gilbert</hi> aduiseth to doe, and to vse the little needle <hi>fol.</hi> 186.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But you say that this needle is altogether needlesse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the instrument will finde the Magneticall Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian by his least declination vnder the Horizon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hauing this needle standing on his foot with a directorie needle, did turne and place this instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ward the East, and after to the Westward, and I found that the more he was turned either way the lesse he did ascend and descend by foure or fiue Degrees or more, then he would doe being set in his Magneticall Meridian, hauing experimented it now diuers times vpon the occasion of your asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But place him perfectly by the directory nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in his Magneticall Meridian, and then you shall obserue him to ascend and descend to his greatest in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination which is his true place from the Horizon,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:178503:20"/>which here in <hi>England</hi> I hold to be about seuenty degrees, although some tables would haue it be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentie and two degrees, but diligent obseruation must cleare this point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreouer in the</hi> 82 <hi>page, you obserue an other error of mine (which you greatly mistake) saying that that end of the Inclinatorie needle which is prepared to hang to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the North, I would haue it formed somewhat heauier then the other end is, as is vsuall in Horizontall needles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed there is a proposition in the 65 page of my booke, that I would haue that end which is touched from the North-end of the Load-stone, to be made lighter to counteruaile the touching which in the leuell ends will sway downe a little, and although you tooke hold of the contrary, yet by looking into the place, I doe obserue something that it may bee you doubt of, the which may be rectified by reason and experience, and therefore we would entreat those Masters and Marriners that trauell to the East-Indies, that they would make triall thereof by hauing two Inclinatory needles fitted for their instrument, or else to haue two instruments, the one needle to be made leuell when he is laied with the Horizon, the other to be a little abated for the sway of the touch, and thus we doe commit this point to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by these mens reports at their returne. Now as concerning the reason, I will alleage to prooue that one end must be a little abated is this: If there should be no detraction of weight from the end of the needle; then when as the traueller shall draw nere vnto the equinoctiall within a Degree,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:178503:20"/>ten mile, or a mile of the same, where the Inclinatory needle will shew very few Degrees aboue the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, because he should become almost leuell with the same, the poles of the world lying very neare the Horizon, in these cases, here reason saith that the ouer-weight of the touch will sway the needle below the Horizon, which should be scarce descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to a leuell with it, as it doth here with vs in the compasses &amp; directory needles that haue there coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoise. And although that with vs the Inclinary needle ascending and discending about seuentie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees from the Horizon, by the conformitie hee maketh with the Magneticall Globe of the Earth, and hanging somewhat prependigular, though a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle a slope, this ouer-weight of the touch doth not altar him much from his true Inclination and place though peraduenture it doth a little, which diligent obseruation may teach vs better hereafter, some few leaues before this.</p>
            <p>I affirmed that if you did sleightly touch the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinatory needle with the North-end of your Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, that it would beeing before leuell with the Horizon now descend vnder the same 20.30. or to what else degrees the heauinesse of the touch swayed him, which practice proceeded from the weight of the touch, this thing then I set downe to follow you in an error the better to demonstrate your owne error vnto you.</p>
            <p>The Inclinatory needle being equally leuell at both ends, is like vnto the beame of a ballance of a paire of fine Scoales, where a graine weight will readily cast the Scoales, yea the Mint Master are so
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:178503:21"/>perfect and exquisite in weighing that their Scoales will declare the twentith part of a graine which they call a Mite. And they haue other lighter subdiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions to droites, periots euen vnto very blankes, whereof they haue 24 in one periote, all which there exquisitnesse in weighing they ordinarily vse; I thinke that these Masters were very fit to <hi>graduat your needle you speake of in the</hi> 59 <hi>page, which you would haue to serue any Latitude.</hi> But (as I haue deliuered before) touch the Inclinatory needle from the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest of it vnto the end vpon the pole or tooth of a very good Load-stone some fiue or sixe times, that he bee perfectly animated with a quicke and full Magneticall vertue, then put him into his instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and you shall obserue that he presently as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth by the vigour of the Magneticall Globe of the earth, composing himselfe to his due hight, as nere as may be, in the North quadrant of our Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spere, and will in no case descend on the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side vnder the Horizon, because that all the Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall conformitie from the earth, is to conuert this needle, so that he ascend on the North-side, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend on the South-side to his due angle hauing much aduised and argued with my selfe about this controuersie, why this Inclinatorie needle naturally and most truely ascending on the North-side of our Hemi-sphere, to make his conformitie with the North superficies and axis of the earth, should be found by common practice of our workemen, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwise to descend on the North-side, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end of the needle to ascend on the South-side; yet I doe finde by Doctor <hi>Gilberts</hi> owne instruments
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:178503:21"/>and his needle well touched and animated, that they doe ascend on the North-side, and not descend as he writeth, and therefore to declare the very cause of this vsuall discent of the needles, being made most artificially and comely by our trimming for distructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on sake, either with a crosse or with some other such loading deuise, whereas it were better and is neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie that the way from the middest of the needles to the ends be alwaies made of equall weight as wyers are, or else to be equally lessened from the middest to the ends, when as they shalbe made leuell before the touch, for I finde that a graine weight laide on the end that ascendeth, causeth him with great speed to descend to about seuenty two degrees, yea halfe a graine doth the same, and being very curious herein I obserue that one mite loadeth him downe in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as low, therefore this needle as I haue said is very carefully to be made, that he may haue his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall position with the axis of the Earth, and in vse I would aduise that obseruation be had whether the strength of the touch doe decay within certaine time or no, as it doth in the directory needle and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe.</p>
            <p>I said imediatly before, that the reason wherefore the North-end of the needle did descend, was either because it was ouer-clogged with some deuise, so that the Magneticall virtue of the whole needle could not erect it aboue the Horizon, or else that the North-end was more heauie then the South-end though it were not so much as one mite, which will easily cast the descent of that end; for all confesse that the making of this needle is very troublesome,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:178503:22"/>that though it be leuell before touching with the Load-stone, yet somewhat else must be done to make the North-end thereof to fall vnto his seuenty two Degrees, which must needs be by abating a little of the South end.</p>
            <p>And what is more vnnaturall and absurd, then to say that the North-pole with vs doth descend, and the South-pole to ascend, for what are the ends of the needle, but the poles of the same; yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding if workemen cannot make the true and naturall ascent of the needle, as afore I haue taught; yet it is a thing worthie to be knowne by experience, whether the aduerse angle which the vnnaturall site of the needle maketh, may bee found to be the true angle answerable vnto the eleuation of the pole, which if it fall out to be true, then the instrument thus furnished may be of profitable vse, though the scituation of the Axis of the needle bee aduerse vnto the site of the Axis of the earth: for we haue obserued that if two wyers of equall length and thicknesse bee thrust thorow their corkes, and after they be animated from the stone, if you doe place the North-end vpward in water, then the wier will compose it selfe in the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neticall Meridian, and also bend a slope North-wards vnto his true angle. After place the other wier in the water with his South-end vpwards, and this wier will also set himselfe in the Magneticall Meridian, making the like angle vnto the South, which the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did vnto the North, so that here it may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected that <hi>ex falsis verum aliquando sequatur,</hi> and thus we leaue this last matter to be approoued by our wise Mistrisse experience.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:178503:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>You tell vs in the</hi> 82 <hi>and</hi> 83 <hi>pages, that for Nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnder the pole if there be any passage that way, that the Inclinatory needle is the onely instrument of the world, being their strengest and held in a direct line with the Axis of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There may be a doubt made of the truth of these words that the needle should be so strong here as you speake, for we cannot finde by any experiment intrauelling that the earth doth conuert and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe Magneticall bodies, by attraction to bee the stronger, although on the Load-stone we finde it to be so. For their is a great Orbe vnknowne to vs and distance betweene the Magneticall Globe of the earth, and the superficies or vppermost part of the same with many interiacent substances, whereby the virtue attractiue is become very weake &amp; Magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal bodies vpon the earth are placed out of the Orbe of attraction, and only the conuerting &amp; composing of them is vigorous and auailable, as wee see in our needles placed farre off from the Load-stone, and this assertion is demonstrated by Doctor <hi>Gilbert,</hi> fol. 195 and 196. where it appeareth, that the Magnet doth no waies attract the needle in his neer Orbe, betweene the equator and the pole, but onely conuert conforme and compose the needle to a certaine Magneticall conformitie with his superfices or his axis, and further hee proueth that the earth it selfe doth not attract the long wier thrust through a corke and swimming on the water, that it should descend to the bottom which it doth not, but onely compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth him a slope ouer the Magneticall Meridian, <hi>fol.</hi> 203. If it should be questioned what vse there is of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:178503:23"/>the Inclinatory needle nere the pole beside his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring of the Latitude, it wilbe difficul to answere, <hi>becauso you doe neither nominate, nor deliuer any profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vse thereof, onely you appoint a great instrument at the pole and a lesse at that equinoctiall, because there he standeth goggingly and vnsteadily,</hi> but no doubt for the reason before alleaged from the conformatiue power, hee is steady in all places alike, and ought to haue his instrument of like greatnesse, for more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acter obseruation, onely it may be that nere the equinoctiall, the heauinesse and grauitie of touch may be some obstacle in his vse, as I haue already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered.</p>
            <p>And also you set downe in the foresaid pages, <hi>That the Horizon tall and directory needles, had need of a counterpose, especially in our Northerne climates,</hi> but I haue imediately before shewed, that it is needlesse against danger of attraction, and only behooueful for equilibration, aswell here as there, <hi>and you doe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell vs to prouide great compasses at and nere the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall, and lesse at the pole, where ther is no vse of any,</hi> neuerthelesse you may obserue if you please, that betweene 80 and 90 degrees, there is a great gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vse of compasses, if first diligent care be had of pricking the Carde, to set downe from what knowne Meridian they departed, a true reconing kept of the way they make, with the trenching and capes of lands viewed from their knowne Meridian, and the distances also esteemed by the quadrat, from the top of the shippe, whose heightof the water is one side of the triangle, so that easily the distance to such Capes is knowne, where it is very conuenient to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:178503:23"/>fasten on of these truncke prospectiue glasses nere and parrallel to the sights, as Master <hi>Edward Wright</hi> did vse to doe, so that with these few rules I hope the Marriner may easily saile in those Northren seas alwaies eschewing to come ouer nere the pole if it may be, which if it should chance he must be sure of his knowne land, &amp; his other accompts, &amp; although the perfect vse of the compasse be very much weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned here, and as it were of no vse for a little space, yet the other rules and positions carefully obserued wilbe sufficient directions, and the skilfull Pilot will easily returne to his knowne Meridian againe. Here I doe greatly desire such as it doth concerne, not to giue ouer the seeking of a passage vnto <hi>Iapan</hi> from the backe side of King <hi>Iames</hi> his <hi>Greeneland,</hi> for that it is discouered that the seas are open from the North of <hi>Iapan</hi> to 63 degrees, where some of our countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haue beene, and the distance from <hi>Greenland</hi> thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cannot be much aboue sixe or seauen hundred leagues, Also I would request all Pilots that saile to <hi>Greeneland;</hi> and vnto the East <hi>Indies,</hi> that they would make a collumne in their table of courses, for to set downe the angle of the Inclinatorie needle euery day as they doe the variation, which no doubt would be a great helpe vnto them to finde the Latitude, by the varietie of tables and meanes set downe in my booke of <hi>Magneticall bodies and Motions.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="corollary">
               <head>A Corollarie.</head>
               <p>His an ancient figment, first deuised by <hi>Aristotle,</hi> that there is a <hi>primū mobile,</hi> or first moueable which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:178503:24"/>because he would haue it to be the heauen where that fixed starres are placed, this first moueable must carrie and turne them all with the Inferiour Planets from the farthest heauens to the moone which is nearest the earth, round about with it, and they that were farthest off this first moueable, followed it more slowly and came short of mouing out of the East in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the West by certaine houres or parts; but the first moueable with his starres fixed in him as in a vault as he imagined, kept and performed the divrnall motion most iustly in twenty and foure houres aboue all the rest.</p>
               <p>But he neuer suspected or could gather by any reason, that the Earth would salue and ease all this infinit labour, by moouing and turning her body easily and exactly, round about in foure and twenty houres. For <hi>Aristotle</hi> being a wise and an acute Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher, looke what he purposed to proue, he laide a large foundation, and vsed most demonstratiue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, beginning from the least pertinent matters and ascending to the greatest; so that this Philosopher is still vulgerly read in the Vniuersities at this day, whereby he hath drawne almost all Schollers to be of his opinion, and although that he writ almost eight bookes before he could well as he thought maintaine this assertion and figment of his <hi>primum mobile</hi> or first moueable; yet by the way he is disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered many times, to haue vsed arguments rather to fit his owne purpose, then to demonstrate the truth, for in speaking of Motion, Time, and place, whereof one of them cannot stand without the other, he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth motion to be circular, right, or oblique, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:178503:24"/>whereas he would appoint right motion to these bodies and eliments, which are not existent of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, but only are by reason &amp; discourse conceiued to be in things mixed and compounded, where the simple elements themselues are not to be found soly and simply existing or being in this world, which he supposed most certainely: for <hi>Galen</hi> hath most plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and truely taught, that no man is able to shew that earth which is called that element earth, and so of the rest, because that alwaies there be some other ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments mixed with them. <hi>Galen</hi> reporteth that <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle</hi> had culled this piece of learning out of <hi>Hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> the father of all good learning, both in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophy and Physicke, and so <hi>Aristotle</hi> tooke that to be existent of himselfe, which was not, and would giue euery one of these elements, not onely a place but also a simple motion, because they were simple and <hi>prime</hi> Bodies; but indeed he gaue these foure ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but two Motions, the one to mooue in a right line vpward, the other accordingly downe-ward; and the Circular motion, which better befitted the whole earth, he bestowed vpon his farre distant bodie of the firmament where the starres were, which was rather to be esteemed a place for sirmer substances, then any compact bodie. Notwithstanding he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth that the earth hath a Globous body, and that it is equilibrated one euery side very fitly for motion, and that it is coeternall with the world, which asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth not onely proue the earth to be very apt for Circular motion, but also that it doth consist of a quint essence, by those his arguments of eternitie. Moreouer as <hi>Aristotle</hi> was deceiued in giuing the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:178503:25"/>enements which were not, a place one aboue an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, so likewise he failed about the place of the first moueable, for when <hi>Hipparchus</hi> an exact obseruer of the fixed starres, and after him <hi>Ptolomie</hi> had obserued that the fixed starres beside the divrnall motion out of the East into the West from the first moueable, were noted and obserued in certaine yeares to moue somewhat out of the West into the East, as also from their Southerly place into the North, this great Astronomer <hi>Ptolomy</hi> was faint to faine two heauens more, beside that where the fixed starre were seated, the outmost and farthest to be the <hi>primum mobile</hi> or first moueable that moued and carried all the starres after him out of the East into the West by his divr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall motion. The second heauen was to make a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in certaine yeares out of the West into the East to guide the starres in that point. And <hi>Aristotles</hi> heauen of his first moueable must lease this name and properties he gaue it, and now is ordained to carry the stars out of their South seate, and to place them more Northerly; because that a simple motion doth onely appertaine vnto a simple body, and the starres hauing three motions must needes haue them from three simple bodies, but certainely these supposed heauens be as thinne, as simple, and therefore it is a wonder how they should hold and carry the starres as was supposed, being thicke bodies that would soone penetrate these heauens vpon the least moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being but the same and one Firmament, expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the earth to the farthest parts of the world that filleth all emptinesse and places, and it agreeth with better reason that God at the Creation gaue
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:178503:25"/>virtue and power to the naturall bodies of the starres to make their motions whether one or many, and not vnto these fained Spheres. Beside we may obserue that this firmament wherein we walke and trauell is filled with the grosse fumes, vapours, and exhalati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons driuen out of the earth, or sucked vpwards by the Sunne and Starres, and after a time of ingrossing for lacke of that heate wherewith they were at first indewed, they fall to this earth againe, being rather violently carried out or drawne, then naturally as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending, which thing also <hi>Aristotle</hi> deliuereth though somewhat doubtfully, as we dayly see in the smoake of our Chimnies, that at the first going out ascend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a little, but after a while flutterateth here and there vncertainely falling againe downe to the earth, whereout it was forced.</p>
               <p>There be many other imperfections or rather im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibilities which will dissable the first moueable, to mooue his vast greatnesse round about in foure and twenty houres, the which is the way he is to make in this time, for this motion must be of that swiftnesse and giddinesse considiring the greatnesse of his body and circumference, farre beyond that which <hi>Aristotle</hi> fained, that he must moue diuers thousands of miles in a second minute of an houre, which is farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond any mans capacitie or conceite any way to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue. But to propound a truer matter which wilbe lesse trouble and no violence to the starres and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, let the body of the earth turne about, out of the West into the East from a naturall virtue, from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her, which thing <hi>Aristotle</hi> also conceited, though he did not apply it, and in the space of a fast pulse, or
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:178503:26"/>one ticking of a small watch, which is held equall with on second minute of an houre, and thus let the earth passe but one furlong as some thinke in this little moment of time and the diurnall motion, will truely be performed by her in foure and twenty houres, without any danger to hie Turrets, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or other buildings, taking along with her all the Cloudes and other exhalations as parts of her, this motion being very easie vnto the earth, considering the greatnesse of her bodie: and though we no way feele this motion of the earth, being carried in so great a Shippe and Arke, farre greater then <hi>Noes</hi> Arke, it maketh no greater maruell that we feele not this mouing no more, then we can perceiue the Sunnes moouing, which notwithstanding we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue to be moued as <hi>Cicero</hi> reporteth, and we may say that we are moouing to and from the Sunne, though we thinke the Sunne to be moued.</p>
               <p>Therefore I may conclude, that the Earth hauing parts very fit for motion, as her Globious bodie with equator and parralels ready and apt to obey all inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall virtue and power, which shall moue and turne her out of the West into the East, in foure and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty houres without any stoppe or stay, either from her owne body, or outwardly by any other body, being fast fixed and firmed with a sure foundation from her creation laide on her two poles, North and South by a strong vigour and virtue, which we haue called else-where Magneticall, because the virtue of North and South is obserued in a stone called the Magner, which kinde of vertue is also demonstrated in the Earth, passing by the Meridians to the poles, as also
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:178503:26"/>experimentally the Inclinatory ring with his needle carried about the Earth vpon a Meridian circle, maketh this Circular motion from the Equator to poles and so backe againe, shewing by his varietie of application and angles, the Altitude of the pole, a matter beneficiall and of great vse, for all sea-men and Marriners as hath beene else-where declared.</p>
               <p>Therefore most naturally and truely the Earth moueth about from the West into the East, in twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and foure houres about the Center of her body, as all the fixed starres doe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Tichobrahe,</hi> and the Sunne doth by others in his due time.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults in printing.</head>
            <p>PAge 1 line 28 for laborius, read and laborius, p. 3 line 2 it is said, re. he is sure, page 3 l. 22 Cabanet r. Cabinet, p. 4 l. 29 Earths r. Earthes p. 6 l. 10 Meridians r. the Meridians, p. 7 l. 24 warne r. warme, p. 8 lin. 17. for much moue, r. much more, p. 9 li. 28 Mathematicke r. Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, p. 10 l. 4 better r. a better, p. 10 l. 8 endt r. end, p. 11 l. 1 riuer Trent r. riuer of Trent, p. 11 l. 22. to carry home, r. to carrie them home, p. 11. lin. 24 in tenth page, r. in the tenth page, p. 12. li. 32 dissagreeing, r. the dissa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing, p. 13 l. 20 flowerdelice r. flowerdeluce, p. 15 li. 32 midst r. midle p. 16. l. 11 that that, r. that the, p. 17 l. 23 to the r. to be the, p. 17 li. 32 al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micanther, r. almicantar, p. 19. li. 29 is a matter, r. it is a matter, p. 20 l. 29 impefections, r. imperfections, p. 21. l. 3 Meridinns, r. Meridians, p. 22 lin. 10 in an, r. into an, p. 22 l. 18 deciued, r. deceiued, p. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> li. 30 Azismuthes, r. Azimuthes, p. 23 l. 5 herd, r. heard, p. 23 l. 25 <hi>Torrida zana,</hi> read <hi>Torrida zonae,</hi> p. 25 l. 4 seemeth, r. seemed, p. 26 l. 5 Noth, r. North, p. 28 l. 5 siling r. filing, p. 28 l. 11 skilfull and righter, rea. skilfully and rightly, p. 28 line 22 weigheth, r. weighed, p. 28 l. 29 Mathematisians, r. Mathematicians, p. 28 l. 30 stars plainly, r. stars, planets, p. 31 l. 16 altar, r. alter, p. 31 li. 32 mint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master r. mintmasters, p. 33 l. 1 needle r. needles, p. 38 l. 2 that fixed, r. the fixed, p. 39 l. 9 that, r. the, p. 40 l. 29 expounded, r. expanded.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>